Guide to the Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
Bambaataa, Afrika hip hop archive,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
8094
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-
600 cubic feet.
Vinyl records and other A/V Recordings, Financial Records, Manuscripts, Memorabilia, Photocopies, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Afrika Bambaataa is an American disc jockey, singer, and songwriter from the South Bronx, New York. Often called the “Godfather” of Hip Hop, Bambaataa has helped to define Hip Hop since it emerged in the South Bronx in the 1970s. One of a handful of Hip Hop's 1970s originators, Bambaataa gave Hip Hop its name, and was the first to define its core artistic elements - DJing, rapping, break dancing, and graffiti art - under one cultural umbrella. His cultural organization, the Universal Zulu Nation, has helped to spread Hip Hop culture throughout the world. His genre-defining 1982 song "Planet Rock" and subsequent electro-funk tracks have become icons of hip-hop and electronic music. In 2007 he was nominated for induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-; Universal Zulu Nation (Organization)
Subjects:
African American youth -- Social life and customs.; Disc jockeys.; Electronic music.; Funk (Music).; Hip-hop.; Hip-hop -- Influence.; Hip-hop -- History. -- United States; Music -- Social aspects.; Race relations.; Rap (Music); Rap (Music) -- Political aspects.; Rap musicians.; Hip-hop -- New York.; Rap (Music) -- New York.; Hip-hop; Rap (Music); Rap musicians; Social history
Places:
Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; New York (State) -- New York; New York (State) -- Bronx; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to collection restricted until completion of processing, with the exception of vinyl records that have been individually cataloged.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Manuscripts
a. School Papers and Assignments
b. Africa Trip
c. Soul Scrapbooks and Music Writing
d. Notebooks and Miscellaneous Manuscripts
e. Lyrics and Poems
f. Bronx River Neighborhood Center
g. Phone and Contact Lists
Series II. Flyers
Series III. Photographs
Series IV. Personal Papers
a. Personal Papers
b. Press About Bambaataa
c. Catalogs and Mail
Series V. Universal Zulu Nation Documents
a. Infinity Lessons
b. Administration
Series VI. Stage Costumes and Clothing
Series VII. Periodicals and Publications
a. Small Press Publications
b. Periodicals
c. Publications from 3410 De Reimer Ave. Bronx, NY
d. Other Publications
Series VIII. Moving images and audio recordings
a. Video cassettes
a. Audio cassettes
Series IX. Music collection
12 inch vinyl
Sureshots and altered/obscured
Numbered by Bambaataa
Annotated, not numbered (Alphabetical by artist)
A-D
E-H
I-L
L-O
P-S
T-Z
Numbers, unknown and various
Second alpha sequence
Cataloged individually
Not annotated (Alphabetical by artist)
A
B
C
D
E
F
G
H
I
J
K
L
M
N
O
P
Q
R
S
Afrika Bambaataa recordings
Renegades of Rhythm Tour
Test pressings and white labels (not yet cataloged)
Compilations (not yet cataloged)
7 inch vinyl
Numbered (not yet cataloged)
Annotated not numbered (not yet cataloged)
No annotations (not yet cataloged)
Acetates and lacquer discs
Cassettes (not yet cataloged)
CDs (not yet cataloged)
Series X. Ephemera
CONTAINER LIST
- Series IX. Music collection
  - Acetate discs/Lacquer discs
    The rarest items in this series are in boxes 104 and 105. All 10 inch discs are in box 104. Box 103 contains the less rare items that were not digitized.
    Removed from original jackets and resleeved in buffered sleeves. If original jacket had post-it note from Renegades of Rhythm tour, the post-it was kept on the jacket. Original jackets are stored behind acetate disc.
    - Meireles E Sua Orquestra - B-2, 1974-2004; SR-08815; Meireles E Sua Orquestra; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Sunshine Sound
      New York, New York
      phonograph records
      Sound recordings
    - Baby Huey - Listen to me, 1974; SR-9676; Baby Huey; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Phonograph records
    - Hubbard, Freddie - In the pocket, 1975; SR-10373; Hubbard, Freddie; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Artisan
    - Bloodstone - Do you wanna do a thing, 1976; SR-10379; Bloodstone; 10 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # 5N-1064; Matrix # ZXDR-58749-DEV 2-25-75 TR
      London Records
      London, United Kingdom
    - Moody, James - This masquerade, 1976; SR-10372; Moody, James; Bland, Ed; Russell, Leon; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Skyhill Publishing Co., Inc.
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Jungle rock (mix by Bambaataa), 1977; SR-06803; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Munich Machine - Get on the funk train (Canadian mix by J.L.), 1977; SR-08810; Munich Machine; J.L.; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - MacDonald, Ralph - Jam on the groove, 1977; SR-08811; MacDonald, Ralph; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # F10006
    - Bobo Drake - Jungle, 1977; SR-10348; Bobo Drake; Drake, Robert; Horne, Jimmy 'Bo'; Love Unlimited Orchestra; Jackson, Jermaine; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Negron, Jay - Hollywood, 1977; SR-10349; Negron, Jay; Village People; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Rare Earth - Happy song, 1977; SR-10350; Rare Earth; Kevorkian, François; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # F10001
    - Salsoul Orchestra - Magic bird of fire, 1977; SR-8808; Salsoul Orchestra; Kevorkian, François; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # F10002
    - Salsoul Orchestra - Magic bird of fire, 1977; SR-8809; Salsoul Orchestra; Kevorkian, François; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Unknown artist - Loose hips; Rump bump, 1978; SR-10380; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      ODO Sound Studios
    - Ramses II - Osiris, 1979; SR-10346; Ramses II; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # F10010
    - Kevorkian, François - Groove city, 1979; SR-10347; Kevorkian, François; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # F10011
    - Chic - Good times, 1979; SR-10352; Chic; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Jimmy[?] - Disco party; Space funk, 1979; SR-10353; Jimmy[?]; Manzell; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Clark, Joseph - Disco boogie, 1979; SR-10355; Clark, Joseph; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Jimmy [?] - Zulu funk, 1979; SR-10359; Jimmy [?]; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Jimmy Jim - Funk jam pt. 2, 1979; SR-10360; Jimmy Jim; Manzell; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Unknown artist - Zulu madness, 1979; SR-10362; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Bambaata[sic] beats; Frank Sinatra, standards, showtunes, 1980; SR-06889; Afrika Bambaataa; Sinatra, Frank; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      ***Has catalog record, no need to include in finding aid?*** Moved from Renegades of Rhythm box 5 to Acetates for digitization
    - Unknown artist - Groove beat, 1980; SR-08814; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Unknown artist - Sophisticated funk, 1980; SR-10351; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Spyder D - Rapple (Big apple rappin)(inst.), 1980; SR-08825; Spyder D; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
      Spyder Music
      Newtroit Records
    - X.D. Prod. - NJRC disco brakes, 1980; SR-10354; X.D. Prod.; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Jimmy Jim - Zulu rainin' hell, 1980; SR-10357; Jimmy Jim; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - AJ Scratch - AJ on the funk box; Flash it to the beat, 1980; SR-10365; AJ Scratch; Furious Five; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Hydraulic Funk - Wild style; Shango message, 1980-1989; SR-10370; Hydraulic Funk; Shango; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Celluloid Records
    - Afrika Bambaataa and the Jazzy 5 - Jazzy sensation (do the gigolo) rap version; Jazzy sensation (do the gigolo) instrumental, 1981; SR-10345; Afrika Bambaataa and the Jazzy 5; Afrika Bambaataa; Jazzy 5; 10 inches; acetate discs | Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Cotton Candy - Havin' fun, 1981; SR-10371; Cotton Candy; Trollinger, Donna; Osaze, Ted; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Tommy Boy
    - Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force - Electric boogieland; Don't you ever forget pt 2 (Shinning stars)[sic], 1982; SR-10341; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force; Grandmixer D.S.T. & the Infinity Four; GrandMixer DXT; Infinity Rappers; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & the Soul Sonic Force - Planet rock, 1982; SR-10343; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soul Sonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Stored for many years in an ill-fitting jacket. Can see an imprint on the label.
    - Shango - Zulu groove, 1983; SR-08816; Shango; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force - Renegades of funk, 1983; SR-08818; Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force - Renegades of funk, 1983; SR-10358; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Afrika Bambaataa and the Soul Sonic Force - Renegades of funk (rough mix), 1983; SR-10363; Afrika Bambaataa and the Soul Sonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Afrika Bambaataa and Soul Sonic Force - Renegades of funk, 1983; SR-08822; Afrika Bambaataa and Soul Sonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
    - Mtume - Would you like to (Fool around); Let's fool around (Word) (Sensual instrumental), 1983; SR-10388; Mtume; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # 49-04088 XXS 171348; Matrix # XXS-171347-1A
      Epic
    - Mtume - Would you like to (Fool around); Would you like to (Fool around), 1983; SR-10389; Mtume; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # 49-04088 XXS 171347; Matrix # XXSS-171347-1B
    - Shango - Let's party down; Thank you for letting me be myself again, 1984; SR-08819; Shango; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force - The cooley (10 minute version); Unity, 1984; SR-10342; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa; Brown, James; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Don One Sound Studio
      Brooklyn, New York
    - Time Zone - World Destruction, 1984; SR-08820; Time Zone; Afrika Bambaataa; Rotton, Johnny; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Time Zone - World Destruction, 1984; SR-08821; Time Zone; Afrika Bambaataa; Rotton, Johnny; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Yellowman - Tell em, 1984; SR-10366; Yellowman; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Yellowman - Strong me strong, 1984; SR-10367; Yellowman; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 106)
    - Afrika Bambaataa and Family - Funk you, 1985; SR-08813; Afrika Bambaataa and Family; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & the Soul Sonic Force - Bambaataa's theme; Funkin' (all the way live) Part 2, 1986; SR-8807; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soul Sonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa & Soulsonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa; Melle Mel; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Bionic kats, 1986; SR-08824; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Bionic kats (inst.), 1986; SR-10361; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Funk Queens - Punk funk railroad, 1987; SR-08823; Funk Queens; Shango; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
    - Unknown artist - Can; And more, 1992; SR-10377; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - Afrika Bambaataa presents Time Zone - What's the name of this nation?...Zulu!; The cooley, 1993; SR-10344; Afrika Bambaataa presents Time Zone; Time Zone; Afrika Bambaataa & the Soulsonic Force; Afrika Bambaataa; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - DJ Soul Slinger - Don't believe (gold edition) (disc one), 1997; SR-08812; DJ Soul Slinger; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # JS-118; Matrix # JS-118A
      Jungle Sky
    - Submomentum - Trinic saga; Deceptive cloaks; Liquid phrase, 1997; SR-10376; Submomentum; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Dub Lab
      Miami, Florida
    - Pressure Drop - It's like that; Got to be surreal; Give yourself up, 1997; SR-10384; Pressure Drop; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # HAND43T2; Matrix # HAND 043 TP2-A1
      Hard Hands
    - Unknown artist - Say my name, 1997; SR-10391-10392; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Matrix # JADE 001-AA1 and MJC-B1
      United Kingdom
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Fire (funk remix), 1999; SR-08036; Afrika Bambaataa; DJ Soulslinger; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
    - DJ Soul Slinger - Zulu transform (Brasil to B-Boy mix), 2000; SR-10385; DJ Soul Slinger; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
    - Holkkonen, Jori - All I see is shadows (Acid Kings remix), 2002; SR-10383; Holkkonen, Jori; Acid Kings; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # F171W; Matrix # B271826-01-A1
      F Communications
      France
    - PJ Harvey - Harvey floorbanger, 2004; SR-10382; PJ Harvey; 12 inches; Vinyl discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # DDB-021-A
      DDB Records
    - Atlanta Disco Band - Do what you feel, 1976-02-19; SR-10378; Atlanta Disco Band; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # 180048A
      Capitol Records, Inc.
      Hollywood, California
    - Floaters - Levitation, 1979-06-27; SR-10374; Floaters; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Catalog # MC 8834 RE
      MCA Whitney
      Glendale, California
    - Moore, Jackie - How's your love life baby (disco vers.); How's your love life baby (instr. vers.), 1979-09-21; SR-10386; Moore, Jackie; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Columbia Records
    - Funky 4 - Superstars, 1981-11-16; SR-10364; Funky 4; Funky Four; Funky Four Plus One More; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
      Sterling sound
    - Mtume, James - Would you like to fool around; In the name of you; Would you like to fool around; In the name of you (inst), 1983-07-27; SR-10387; Mtume, James; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
    - Earth, Wind & Fire - Speed of love; Magnetic, 1983-10-10; SR-10381; Earth, Wind & Fire; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      CBS
    - Awesome Foursome - Funky breakdown, 1983-11-01; SR-10356; Awesome Foursome; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 105)
      Streetwise
    - O'Neal, Alexander - Criticize, 1987-08-23; SR-9681; O'Neal, Alexander; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      CBS Records
    - Jazzy Jay - Chillin' in the studio (Side A), 1987-10-27; SR-10368; Jazzy Jay; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 106)
      Catalog # ST 100
      Strong City Records
      Truetone Records
      Haworth, New Jersey
    - Jazzy Jay - Chillin' in the studio (Side B), 1987-10-27; SR-10369; Jazzy Jay; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 106)
    - Afrika Bambaataa & Family - Sho nuff funky (side one), 1988-01-26; SR-9677; Afrika Bambaataa & Family; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      EMI Records
    - Afrika Bambaataa & Family - Sho nuff funky (side two), 1988-01-26; SR-9678; Afrika Bambaataa & Family; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # 12 EM 57
    - Afrika Bambaataa & Family - The light (side one), 1988-01-27; SR-9679; Afrika Bambaataa & Family; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Catalog # 064 7 90423
    - Afrika Bambaataa & Family - The light (side two), 1988-01-27; SR-9680; Afrika Bambaataa & Family; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
    - Afrika Bambaataa - Ndodemnyama (free South Africa) (side B), 1989-10-13; SR-08817; Afrika Bambaataa; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Warlock Records
    - Justice System - Dedication to Bambaataa, 1994-10-24; SR-10390; Justice System; 12 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 103)
      Sterling Sound
    - Unknown artist - Blackwater, 1997-05-06; SR-10375; 10 inches; Acetate discs; Lacquer discs (Box 104)
      Caroline Records